Natalie Spiska: There we go. Perfect. Alright, well, to start, if you could just briefly talk about what kind of technology your program currently uses, including any sort of wearable technology or stats website like Clip?
Coach: So we use, for Stats, we use, Decade.
Coach: And guys have to turn their… That's in by 9 o'clock.
Coach: usually the morning after. If we're on the road at a tournament, I just… we just get it done at the end of the tournament.
Coach: I… I actually… Dive deep into our stats. I don't really do…
Coach: one tournament, I'm looking for trends, so I'll do… I like 6 rounds, so if I can get to 6 rounds, which we've played 6 rounds so far.
Coach: So, I like to look at…
Coach: tournament rounds, not practice. I don't really have a… unless it's qualifying, we don't track that.
Coach: If they're just playing, like, 9 holes and trying to hit situational shots, we don't track any of that.
Coach: We have a Zen putting green upstairs, which is a green that moves, it's pretty cool.
Natalie Spiska: Yeah.
Coach: We get a lot of use out of that.
Coach: Some of the guys are aim-pointers, like me, and…
Coach: They'll set it to be able to calibrate themselves a little bit better.
Coach: We have a Quintech, we use it lightly. We have a sand putt lab that we use a lot.
Coach: We have two quads, that we use a ton of, and then we use… we have,
Coach: two track bands, and apparently Trackman plural is track bands, which I didn't… I didn't know that.
Natalie Spiska: Weird, truckmen.
Coach: I thought it was gonna be TrackMen, but it's TrackMen. We do a ton… we do a ton of combines. We have a weekly
Coach: combine requirement. We have a…
Coach: One that we set up from 50 yards to 150 yards that they have to have a certain score on.
Coach: And we'll… we'll keep a leaderboard of that.
Coach: Other than that, I, I like…
Coach: Using the technology indoors, obviously, since this semester has been pretty white, and we haven't been able to get outside much.
Coach: It's been very productive to track numbers and
Coach: To, work on some wedge…
Coach: watch distances, so that's been productive. But other than that.
Coach: Yeah, we don't have anything… anything else other than that. It's a nice collection, we're very blessed.
Natalie Spiska: Yeah, I was gonna say, that's… that's a lot of technology that you guys have, especially Decade. I've used it in the past, but, like, very briefly. But, like, how has… how has Decade been implemented into your guys', like, training program?
Coach: Sure, so we have our guys go on track, man, and they set up
Coach: On… we have one account for each guy, and we have them track
Coach: There's shot dispersion ellipses, so that we can discuss with them
Coach: What shots to hit under certain conditions.
Coach: Especially on par 3s,
Coach: you know, when I coached on the women's side, we didn't see too many 220, 240-yard par 3s. We're seeing quite a few of them now.
Coach: Yeah. On the men's side. So, I think it's important to understand
Coach: What a player's tendencies are, and you know, the nice thing is we can…
Coach: Really take some deep dives, and after a tournament.
Coach: Where all their stats are in,
Coach: Decade actually has, like, a shot tracker, like a… like a shot link.
Coach: That the guys put in, and I can track how we play
Coach: Or what it looks like, or how we played each hole.
Coach: Which is really.
Natalie Spiska: Interesting.
Natalie Spiska: Yeah.
Coach: Yeah, so…
Coach: you know, if a guy's like, oh man, I was standing in the middle of the fairway to make double bogey, well, like, how'd you make double bogey? And then you can actually go in and see that
Coach: They hit it in the bunker, hit it over the green.
Coach: Chipped it to 20 feet, and then 2-putt.
Natalie Spiska: Yeah.
Coach: I think it's a great thing to use, because I think college golfers talk 68, shoot 78, and act 88, so…
Coach: it's one of those things where we think… and it's a human thing, I think. We think we're way better than we are, so I think it brings you down into a realistic world when you're like, oh yeah, I, you know, I…
Coach: I played number 420. Alright, well, why did you do that? Well, I drove into the bunker twice.
Coach: and then I got it underneath that lip. Well, maybe you shouldn't have hit driver there, right? And…
Coach: it does a lot with course management. Obviously, the videos are fantastic. And full disclosure, I'm a good, close, personal friend of
Coach: Scott Fawcett.
Natalie Spiska: Oh, nice!
Coach: I was one… I… yeah, I went to one of his first,
Coach: lectures that he did at Baltistrrol back in…
Coach: like, 2014 or 15, and I was just enamored with it. I went away from it for a little bit.
Coach: But I think the educational component in Decade is really, really good.
Coach: You know, some of the drills, and then obviously the talking about how to practice, shot dispersion.
Coach: Because I'm sure [Author's Coach] could tell you the same thing. I'm gonna tell you here, that…
Coach: Even if we say it, if Scott Fawcett says it, it's completely different, it's so much more powerful, so…
Natalie Spiska: Likely, yeah.
Coach: I like to have as many, yeah, I like to have as many, arrows in my quiver as possible, so…
Coach: We do a lot with that decade.
Natalie Spiska: Yeah, that sounds good. How's the use of technology in your program changed over, like, the last few years?
Coach: Yeah, we used to have to beg guys to put stats in, and it was.
Natalie Spiska: Yeah.
Coach: hard, but as our team has gotten more and more competitive over the years.
Coach: It's really not so much of a thing.
Coach: Trackman and the quads have been…
Coach: Like, I don't think we hit a ball upstairs without a launch monitor on it.
Coach: It's very rare that we hit a ball upstairs, unless somebody's working on a feel, or they're working on a swing lesson.
Coach: something they're doing with their Home Pro.
Coach: Just because, you know, when we're upstairs and we don't have ball flight, you want to see what the ball's doing.
Coach: Because obviously that's the most important thing, because you want the golf ball to be your coach, and I talk about that a lot.
Coach: But, you know, I think a lot more guys are using
Coach: The launch monitors, with a… we just hired an assistant coach.
Coach: And he's become really proficient in the sand putt lab, so our guys hop on that at least once a week. That's been really good. That's like a track man for putting, so it's been very productive.
Natalie Spiska: Yeah, I was gonna say, we had a sand putt lab, and we only used it briefly, because it was loaned to us by one of our… my teammates' coaches, but how do you.
Coach: Huh.
Natalie Spiska: the Samputt Lab as, like, that track man? Like, are you just checking to make sure your stroke's online, or…
Natalie Spiska: How's it?
Coach: Yeah, I mean, I think sometimes you can give athletes too much information.
Coach: So, the great thing about [Assistant Coach] is he doesn't let them take too deep of a dive and try to break down their putting stroke too much.
Coach: Yeah.
Coach: It has a feedback system in the most recent update, where it'll tell you what the clubface is doing, if it's open or closed at impact.
Coach: which is something I harp on. We want to make sure we're returning the club as…
Coach: As close to square or zero as possible.
Natalie Spiska: Yeah.
Coach: But I think technology, especially with your generation, because you guys are so smart with technology that it… it could be…
Coach: It could be, detrimental as well. When we first got TrackMan.
Coach: We had two guys that were upstairs all the time.
Coach: And [Player 1], who, was one of the best players to ever play at [University].
Coach: [Player 1] played, would hit balls in the thing and wouldn't really care. Just wanted to know how far is the ball going?
Coach: And then, how far, you know, how much thin he had on the golf ball.
Coach: And then, his best friend growing up, [Player 2], unfortunately, he didn't realize how much all of the information would bother him.
Natalie Spiska: So we go to our first tournament, and he's just freaking out. He's like, I can't believe I got so many things going on in my mind.
Coach: So, when we got back, he and I were hitting balls upstairs, and I just turned all the tiles off.
Coach: And just left on, you know, carry number.
Coach: And club head speed, because he wanted to see how far… how hard he was hitting it.
Coach: that was… that was massive for [Player 2]. He was a great player. I mean, he was a [University] Player of the Year, and that was massive for him, because he needed…
Coach: To be able to just see how far he hit it.
Coach: And then you have some kids you probably have on your team that need to know everything. Angle of attack.
Coach: You know, you know, our, backspin, sidespin…
Coach: Low point, that's become a new hot one.
Natalie Spiska: Yeah.
Coach: You know, it's… it's… you gotta be careful how you use the technology, for sure.
Coach: And the other thing is, I don't really want to be a guy who leans on technology when you're trying to coach golfers to score.
Coach: Because… the search for perfect, and I'll say this a thousand times to our guys.
Coach: The search for perfect really ruins a lot of golfers.
Coach: Especially young ones, because…
Coach: You know, you know kids that once you hand them a scorecard, they play… they play completely different.
Coach: And when they're on the range, they look lost.
Coach: But if you get them out in a match against somebody, it's… it's something pretty nice.
Coach: But then again, you get some kids who really need to know techno… need to know their numbers.
Coach: Their launch conditions and all that other garbage, but…
Coach: I'm not chasing or coaching golf swings, I'm chasing guys that could put a scorecard together.
Natalie Spiska: Yeah, I definitely agree with that. Also, being, like… I wouldn't say I'm too reliant on technology, but I definitely do like to know what my numbers are around a certain area, so, yeah. So what do you do… what do you do if…
Coach: If your numbers are off.
Natalie Spiska: If my numbers are off, this happened to me last season. Honestly, I didn't look at or video my swing for, like, the entirety of last spring semester. I knew what was happening, I was just like, as long as I'm, like, hitting it where I need to go, it doesn't need to be pretty. So for me, I have to completely shut it off. I'm not looking at anything.
Natalie Spiska: It's gotten a lot better now, so a big thing for me is club path, because I have a tendency to just go a little bit over the top, and I really, really don't like it. So, if my club path is positive, I like that. If it's negative, it bothers me, but…
Natalie Spiska: I've gotten better at with it through the years.
Coach: That's good. That's good. Well, at least you can… at least you can self…
Coach: analyze and then fix that on your own. There's a lot of people who can't. They need that technology.
Natalie Spiska: It's taken me a while to get to this point, though, I will admit, so…
Coach: Sure, golf isn't easy, it's hard. Ball's on the ground, you gotta get it off the ground, it's not easy.
Natalie Spiska: Yeah, exactly. Are there any particular skill areas that you think technology has the biggest impact?
Natalie Spiska: Like, ball striking, in your putting, short game.
Coach: I think centerness of strike with a putter, so making sure that the sand putt lab is calibrated correctly, flat, and level.
Coach: I think that's massive, because the center of the strike
Coach: for a putt is so massively important, and they see guys on TV with a bad camera angle, and they're like, oh, well, this guy's not center… this guy's not hitting it on the center. Well, he may not be setting up on the center, but he's most certainly striking it on the center. If you go back and you look at it.
Coach: I think that the really good stuff
Coach: that Trackman is moving towards. They have an AI version now, have you seen Tracy?
Natalie Spiska: Tracy, yeah, I've seen… I haven't used it, but one of my teammates was using it, and she's like, Tracy hates my swing. I go, okay.
Coach: So I… I…
Coach: I hop on there, and I taught for a living, back in the day, and
Coach: I think it's genius what they're doing, is they're taking the information and they're telling you what to work on. And then they give you three options, right? Like, they give you three… like, for me, it's dynamic loft, because my pelvis stalls and I get a little flippy.
Coach: So, I work on that, and there's… the great thing is, talking to the track band folks, I'm like, how close are you guys away from wiping out
Coach: like, human instructors.
Coach: And they've made a commitment internally that they just won't do that.
Coach: So, obviously, Tracy doesn't tell you what to work on, like, oh, you need to get the handle more forward. It just… it just gives you numbers of, alright, your dynamic loft for a 7-iron is, I don't know, like, 30… 36 or something like that.
Coach: And,
Coach: you know, it'll tell you, give you a feedback of where it needs to be. I think that's… that's really great.
Coach: And what you could probably use, Tracy, with is your path.
Coach: And telling you where your path is, and giving you feedback.
Coach: But other than that, I think,
Coach: The impact part of Trackband is massive. I think that's really big, like, when you can go in to go impact location.
Coach: I think that's really important, but… I love the fact that
Coach: you can get proper distance numbers indoors with a quad and a trackman now. Trackman, when it first came out, wasn't very good indoors.
Natalie Spiska: Yeah.
Coach: From… yeah, because we don't have a lot of ball flight where we're at upstairs in Gample.
Coach: So the quad has been fantastic. The guys love it, too. You can do competitions on it, and combine type of events on the quad as well.
Natalie Spiska: Has the putting green that you also mentioned, has that helped in any way of being able to use those certain greens and slopes? Because we have something similar, it just, like, adjusts, but it's… it's not that good for, like.
Natalie Spiska: You know, long distance, obviously.
Coach: You want to plug you?
Natalie Spiska: I believe it is a putt view, it's just a flat surface that moves up and down for, different angles, so…
Natalie Spiska: So ours is a Zen putting green.
Natalie Spiska: Okay.
Coach: It's from England.
Coach: We have 1, 2… we have 5 holes on it.
Coach: And all four corners…
Coach: It, like, starts like this, but you can turn it… you can actually bend it, like.
Coach: Like a foam noodle. You can bend it like a foam noodle.
Natalie Spiska: Interesting.
Coach: Yeah, it's… it's really good. I think, I want to get the new turf that they have, it's like lamb wool or something, to where it's a lot more smoother. We have a synthetic turf top right now.
Coach: Yeah, I mean, it's… it's… it's been good for breaking putts.
Coach: You know, and we don't… we don't go crazy. I mean, I set it up to do uphill putts if I have guys that aren't getting it.
Coach: To the hole, or having a hard time getting it to the hole.
Coach: But, like, I say all this… not only to say that
Coach: Like, I just love a good old-fashioned golf ball, or a…
Coach: Or, you know, like a putting string.
Coach: Yeah. You know, I… I like…
Coach: Putt-out has a new thing that I pull out at golf camps all the time.
Coach: It's their wacky ball, it's got a flat side and a round side.
Coach: I think that's really great, because,
Coach: Hitting the… hitting a ball with a… putter…
Coach: And returning it square is so hard. Or, just like an old-school…
Coach: Line completely around a golf ball, or a tailor-made stripe golf ball, and just having people roll that perfectly.
Coach: You know, those… those are great training ads, and there's zero technology in those things.
Coach: So, you know, I… I think that's… that's… that's a… that's a big thing in my arsenal, for sure.
Natalie Spiska: Yeah, it's a really good point, especially since, like you were talking about, people just get, like, overloaded with information, too, so sometimes it's better to be just basic.
Natalie Spiska: Are there any types…
Coach: Yeah, go ahead, I'm sorry. Go ahead, I'm sorry.
Natalie Spiska: Go ahead. Oh, no, I was just gonna ask the next question, so you can finish your point if you want to.
Coach: I've seen the blast motion device, have you seen that?
Coach: I don't believe so. Is it for putting? It's a putting device? It's for putting. It goes on the top of the putter.
Coach: there's,
Coach: it doesn't give the best numbers, and, like, it's not always correct. So, like, that was a hot…
Coach: item, and it was, like, 110. And it still collects a ton of information that they don't share with you.
Coach: But it's… it's frustrating, because it'll give you bad information back.
Coach: But then there was another company that…
Coach: God, I can't remember the name of it right now, but it… instead of capturing, like, 60 frames per second, it was, like, 336…
Coach: frames per second, and it was super accurate. Oh, it was called Biomech, and the company just closed. It just closed. It was a great putting device, but it just…
Coach: there wasn't enough interest in it, so… but you can have some bad information, too, like…
Natalie Spiska: You know, if people don't know how to read a track, man.
Coach: That's tough.
Coach: And people try to read that thing, and they don't know what they're doing. That's a bad deal, so…
Natalie Spiska: Yeah.
Natalie Spiska: Are there any technologies that you've tried to use, and then you ended up not using it?
Coach: Yeah, that, that…
Coach: That last motion, I worked with it for about a year, and I just decided to punt it.
Coach: There's some new ones that are really good.
Coach: One of our former players is a… is one of the top punting instructors in the world. His name's [Player 3]. He's from… he's actually…
Coach: [Area near Author].
Coach: named… yeah, his name's [Player 3]. If you go find him on Instagram, he's fantastic. He works with a ton…
Coach: of, he works with [Player 4], he works with, oh, God,
Coach: [Player 5], and on his,
Coach: But he's, he's based in [City] now, but he always… if you ever… if you need to talk to somebody else about technology and the golf world, he's a great guy I could connect you with.
Coach: And he's a great kid. Yeah, I mean, I don't…
Coach: when we're on the road, I don't really want to see a lot of, like, oh, what are my numbers? Like, what's my angle of attack, and… I mean, the change of an angle of attack at a tournament site is psychotic. I don't know who would ever try to do that. So I try to keep the iPads just with carry numbers and…
Coach: [Player 3] is great with that, keeping it… keeping it dumbed down so it's not too technical.
Natalie Spiska: Sounds good. Are there any types of performance tools or insights that you wish existed, but don't yet? And if you can't think of anything, is there any sort of technology you would get for your program instead?
Coach: You know, I… I don't think there's something… yeah, I… I do wish that there was a device
Coach: For putting, that would tell you…
Coach: Exactly where the putter is aimed, in real time.
Coach: So, like, it… and it wasn't, like, some big, bulky device that goes on top of the putter. I wish there was a way…
Coach: Because Sam Putt Lab does that, but you gotta look at the screen. I would like something with a little bit more audio feedback.
Coach: And, you know, stuff like that. Yeah, not…
Coach: I'm not the brightest bulb of the bunch, so I don't know if I could think of something that would be…
Natalie Spiska: Yeah. No worries.
Coach: edge.
Natalie Spiska: I test… tested these questions on [Coach 1], and he was fully stumped, so I was like, it's an interesting question to ask, because maybe someone does have something to think, but that's why I was like.
Coach: Dude.
Natalie Spiska: Just in case you can't think of anything, anything else, but…
Coach: I mean, obviously with putting, I think putting is… if you look at the make rates on the PGA Tour, they're going… they're going the wrong way.
Natalie Spiska: And I wonder why that is. Obviously, I think the Greens…
Coach: In professional golf are becoming much faster.
Natalie Spiska: Yeah.
Coach: The ball is harder.
Natalie Spiska: So I think the ball skids a little bit more.
Coach: you know, I think [Coach 1] a lot smarter than I am, so I don't feel too bad.
Natalie Spiska: Sounds good. My final two questions, what role do you see technology playing in collegiate golf in the next 5 to 10 years, and if you think that'll even change the recruiting process in a way?
Coach: You know, I was surprised that Trackman numbers have not… gotten…
Coach: More and more involved in the recruiting process, which has been interesting.
Coach: you know, I think it's getting there, especially when you have some coaches telling recruits that they won't recruit
Coach: The kid, unless he has 165 ball speed and those type of things, but…
Coach: you know, I come from a place where I've got to help players develop, so I think our weight room and our… our process upstairs in our indoor facility, we can get a guy faster, we have. We've gotten a bunch of guys faster. Even fast guys, we've gotten faster, so…
Coach: You know, I think the…
Coach: the combine information, I think that's gonna be really, really good, because it's like a… it's like a…
Coach: A standard in the golf world.
Coach: That, you know, if you tell me that you have a full bag combine score of
Coach: 80 or above, that's pretty darn good.
Coach: You know?
Coach: Yeah, I mean, I think the 3D motion analysis stuff is gonna start creeping into college golf, because it's becoming more and more affordable.
Coach: And some schools, like us and [University], have 3D motion labs on campus.
Coach: I don't know if [University] does, but we do.
Coach: Yeah, I think… Yeah, I don't know. I mean, I think… Yeah, I think…
Coach: I think it will, but I think it's gonna be more…
Coach: Like, launch monitor information than anything else?
Natalie Spiska: And overall, would you say the technology has had a positive or negative impact on your program?
Coach: Oh, it's been positive for us indoors, because we're, you know, [Assistant Coach] and I are pretty diligent about making sure they don't
Coach: They're not messing around with trying to figure out too much information, so…
Natalie Spiska: Yeah.
Coach: We've got a good group of guys, they're not… They're not,
Coach: you know, they're not getting out of hand when it comes to numbers, which is important to me. I…
Coach: I… like, again, like I said before, I think the search for perfect really gets in the way.
Coach: like you, like… like what you were saying, it's like, yeah, if I know it's going off, I can fix it, so that's great. I think you should be able to.
Coach: But I think there are a lot of golfers that try to play in college that try to search for perfect.
Coach: And it just derails them all the time.
Coach: Or they get somewhere and can't play.
Natalie Spiska: Yeah.
Natalie Spiska: Well, that sounds good. Thank you so much. Wait, I'm gonna, stop my recording real quick.